welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
well welcome to the Stella I'm Peter
Lindbergh Stewart of the stola Estelle
is a place for us to cohere and dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of this moment and today is the
first of a bi-weekly series called
dia logos and I imagine if you're here
you have some idea what dia logos is
you've might have watched John Verve a
key talk about it and you might have
watched d logos in action with John guy
Jordan Hall and Chris and so today we're
trying to see if we can you know get
more people involved in this in this
process of the Ilocos so today we have a
guy thanks doc and then we have John for
Vicki Jordan and Chris couldn't make it
today but they might make it and
subsequent weeks so we have a series of
exercises that I think I will walk us
through and you got the Google Doc to to
take a look at it right now if you like
and we have two hours today something
said I'm just gonna take and guy and you
can kind of explain how we're gonna do
it and then guy you just let me know
when you need people to be put into
breakout rooms okay great thank you so
yeah so let me switch it to so I could
see all the boxes on my screen all right
welcome everybody thanks for coming so a
couple of things I just want to set a
little bit of context for today and also
for this aunt this is going to be an
ongoing you could say experiment into
exploring what dialogo says right and
how it is specifically how it integrates
with a series of as John would say
ecology of practices one of them being
circling which is the the one that that
I was I co-founded and the and and how
that can can be a basis of and rise into
the logos to dial dye logos and and and
then back into something like circling
and have those you
truly afford each other into something
that I've experienced is quite stunning
and it's going to be kind of the talos
right or the the the whisper that we're
listening to throughout the whole thing
so everything that we're going to be
doing is gonna be listening to this that
the whisper of the logo so and see see
if we can catch it sales so - so to
speak and so as you can tell already the
thing we're gonna I really want to
invite you in terms of how you
participate is is really one understand
that we're all in an experiment together
this is very experimental right this is
we're gonna engage into a lot of Series
play we're gonna do a lot of
participation there's not gonna be much
kind of lecture per se there may be some
of it right as it as it makes sense to
do so
but really what we're gonna be doing is
going into different practices right and
finding out what happens and then coming
back and explore and what happened in
making adjustments and then most likely
it'll go back and forth right in that so
we're all going to be part of an
unfolding discovery of what what dialo
gose is and how it works and
specifically how we can begin to start
to look at how we can make of it become
something accessible and available to
the culture I submit take it out of just
take it out of something kind of obscure
and and philosophical and really bring
it and make it available to in a way
that could possibly even scale and so
what I would say is I really invite
everyone to as Fromme would say is to is
to is to come from the being vote today
right like really start from start from
the place of rather than participating
in order to get something right or or to
have something or to possess something
is that let's just start by really being
like start by the being mode of really
like being in an open to and and embody
the very thing that we're working with
today
that's probably the best way to
participate John anything anything you
want to say anything you want to add
yeah I guess a few pointers just so
maybe we have some shared terminology
I think of dialectic as if as a specific
psycho technology designed to scaffold
us into the process and the practice of
do logos dialogo C is something that has
to sort of catch fire for us dialectic
is just getting us there where we can
leap into the flame so to speak and so
try to remember that the point of the
dialectic practice is all ultimately to
catch the logos in both senses of the
word to catch it but also the sense of
contagion to be caught up in it and so
it's very important to think of what
we're doing here today the formal aspect
of it as not the final thing this is
very much a scaffolding thing that's
designed to take you it's like the
things you do to try and generate an
insight you know you don't just I don't
have an insight you can't just make it
happen but that doesn't mean you can
just sit passively there's lots of
things you do to scaffold your
relationship to the world or to the
situation so that insight is more
afforded dialectic is the formal
scaffolding that affords the collective
insight flow that is the logos so it's
important to keep those two in mind and
the relationship between them
and just checking is there anybody here
that is does not want any insights just
just make sure it's just so I know so I
know who are listening to is there
anybody here that's like didn't
understand anything about do logos this
is the first time you're hearing it
you're like I was here for an MOA
seminar what are you guys talking about
like everyone has some kind of semblance
of videos that he doesn't know is that
correct James I could use a little more
okay James have you just have you seen
any of
of my dialogues and videos or John's or
the ones with John just a little bit but
yeah okay then that I'm just gonna take
it that you know enough just to be here
for sure yeah yeah okay what's that
picture
you're totally fresh okay great so
Viktor do you have any familiarity with
the concept of being in the flow State
yes so what's interesting is the flow
state is often described even by
Csikszentmihalyi from a mono logical
point of view of it's just you and the
world and that's very interesting
because actually there kinds of
circumstances that both are most
conducive to the flow state are
biological relationships between people
and so you can think of
part of what via logos is is we're
trying to get a collective flow State
between multiple people a sort of
cascade of insights such that the point
of the practice the point where you get
that leap I was mentioning is when two
people get to a place that they couldn't
have gotten to individually on their own
you've probably had that in some of
those great conversations in your life
the conversation took on a life of its
own and you got to a place and the other
person got to a place they couldn't get
to that's basically what we're talking
about here thank you and so if we could
have that kind of flowing conversation
that is also conducive to the
cultivation of wisdom that would be the
project sort of in a nutshell does that
helpful Victor that works good a shot
right and so so just a little bit more
context about today so we're gonna be
doing is today we're mostly just gonna
be we're gonna do some some exercises
one where we split up into pairs
and I'll give instructions for each one
one in which we will split up into three
groups of three and the other one which
will be in groups of four we'll be
putting the instructions in the chat we
also sent a Google Doc with some of the
instructions so when you're in the room
you'll know what to do and then we'll
probably come back in and then enter
into something larger group oriented and
so the thing about the prep about about
practices just to give a little context
of kind of lego because some of them
we're going to encourage a particular
kind of productive struggle if you will
right and and why why go through that
trouble that struggle and it's
interesting because they think about
this in terms of any place where you're
doing any kind of exercise right where
you're trying to increase some capacity
or build some strength or sharpen some
skill it usually involves I think almost
always involves some kind of the
exercises of the kind of constraint
right where you have to you can't you
can use some muscles and you can't use
others I was thinking about when rocky
showed up as you know he trained to be a
southpaw even though he wasn't right
that that you know they they tied his
arm up and he could he had to like just
use the left hand so we're gonna be
doing a bunch of different the different
kinds of exercises where we're putting
some constraints around it to exercise
and work muscles that you may not be
used to working right such that they can
eventually start to take on a life of
them their own and enter into your life
in a way that's like just it starts to
happen spontaneously right so so really
like a lot of what we're doing is really
gonna be twofold as one what like John
and I will be experimenting with what
what's the right what are the right
practices what is the what are the right
constraints right and and we're gonna be
working together and in looking at your
experience together and making
adjustments you know accordingly but the
the point is really you could say the
the ultimate horizon that were what that
we're moving towards right is not
so that you can show up and like do the
practices as the wrote but such that the
capacities that those practice open up
afford something to come naturally in
your life right in a more spontaneous
way so that's that's the that's why if
it's if it's weird and like you feel
discord innate it and it's like
frustrating and all the things that come
with effort right I always wanted to say
this is this is this is this is what the
yeah this is what the effort affords
what we're moving towards I'll sound
good okay good
right on so let's I'm gonna go ahead and
set you up for the first exercise that
we're gonna be doing and this is the
ground in it's really this one is to
really start to bring our awareness into
the present moment and especially the
present moment in a relationship with
somebody else right so basically what
we're gonna we're gonna do is we're
gonna break everyone up into into into
pairs and you're gonna have really
simple instructions with the person that
you're that you're with and the
instructions are this you're gonna
you're gonna one person the first person
who goes is going to just simply say
this you just get really present then
you say being with you I'm experiencing
or I'm noticing or I'm feeling right and
then you say what you're experiencing
noticing and feeling preferably in
relationship to them right and then when
you get done talking when you complete
that sentence then the other person will
say hearing that now I'm noticing
experiencing feeling and then describe
whatever that is and when you get done
sharing that then the other person says
hearing that now I'm experiencing
noticing feeling now the response what
you say may or may not have anything to
do with what they actually said the
intention is just to reveal what it's
like what you're noticing what you're
experiencing in the present moment being
with this person right
and in the goals is to stay in the
descriptive level so I'll just kind of
act out a little example like just so
you can get a sense of it
so it'd be something like if I you know
it's me and myself right it's I'm the
other person I just I would stop and I
just take a deep breath
and I would say being with you right now
I'm noticing a tickly feeling that feels
like a silliness and I noticed myself
smiling because I can see in my own face
and I'm feel glad to be here with you
and then I turn around and I say hearing
that I'm noticing a glow in my heart
because you occur so young and vibrant
guy you get younger by the day I say
hearing that like oh thank you I've
gotten yes and in the goal is to really
find out what you say is to disclose
yourself to the present moment being
with this person and back from forth and
you can just notice what happens as that
cycles okay and we're gonna do that for
a total of four minutes it's any
questions okay fantastic
all right let's break them up into pairs
one room will have three people but
everyone else says - all right looks
like we're back yeah so welcome back
everybody
what's that let's just take a couple of
shit let's take a couple shares what was
that like what did you notice how did it
impact you what was surprising what was
daunting what was yeah let's take a
couple shares it's going to raise your
hand so I can see it
Paul Paul Maloney so what what what for
me it it was it was awkward at first and
like but I think we both warmed up and
you know sort of like it it's there
there was a point at which and Alexei
gave me the comment he said you know
hearing hearing you say that I felt like
the edge came off and you know I felt
like I had an edge and then there was a
point at which we transitions and you
know join you talk all about for state I
feel like that's when we started to sort
of get into that flow state anyone else
yes
you know once there you Albert Crabb
grab yes done myself hey John I'm I'm
very familiar and pretty comfortable
with these exercises and yet it's just
so amazing how you know just just
dropping into the experience it's still
kind of amazing and and wonderful you
know because something can happen very
very quickly that even if one is
relatively comfortable in their own
shell you know that that resonance the
atonement that arises with another just
you know is it's just it's very it's
very expansive
just a very warm positive experience
I appreciate it what you said about even
though this is kind of comfortable and
somewhat familiar
I basically heard you say every time I
dip into it there's something that I
can't just represent as a memory there's
something that goes beyond that that
every time it's like oh yeah even though
I've maybe you've experienced 8000 times
there's something very alive and real an
original about the experience yeah
Lauren I'm not even going to lose it
Lauren Buena Vista how did I do
it's beautiful in a sense that as we
connected with my partner
we were resonating and my partner Ben
was putting the words right in my mouth
as he was saying it it's as if like I
was just thinking about the exact same
thought moments before as he was saying
it and I feel myself like speaking to my
meet to a mirror in front of me and one
thing that resonated to me the most was
this desire for something that we is
real that is going to be formed through
our connection and then as the breakout
rooms were closing actually I just
rushed to type my email address so that
van can contact me because there's this
feeling of like I want to be intentional
and real be by being here and when I
sent him my email address he said like
oh that's why your name is familiar
because I have been seeing you at the
discord server and then that gave me
this flash of familiarity and saying
like yes we are both in the awakening
for meaning crisis server so it means
the same the the connection is not gonna
end in this zoom meeting it's nice to
meet you Lorraine hi nice to meet you
also John I've been in one I asked a
question for you for the disco server
which I missed unfortunately awesome
okay so let's
let's John anything anything you want to
say or add before we before I go to the
next exercise just wanted to riff a
little bit on what the reen scent said
and this sense of and it's appropriate
how to think about it though it's Greek
word for Leah it means this kind of
intimacy not sexual intimacy but this
kind of intimacy and what's gonna happen
hopefully at least what what guy and I
try to figure out is how that
interpersonal intimacy picks up on what
Loreen says the the intimacy with man
was also created in her along in for an
intimacy with what's real and addressing
both of those longings in a coordinated
fashion as part of what we're searching
for here today part of what we're
searching for here today oh well said
which actually leads us into the next
and next bringing in another level in
this exercise okay so one of the things
about when we say what we notice or what
we're experiencing or what we're feeling
if we're describing what we're
experiencing right there's a way we're
actually we've done something where the
communication is not like most of the
communications in our lives
probably necessarily so right which are
try our triangular meaning there's
usually me you and what we're talking
about right and so what we just did
before was we kind of in a certain sense
we we kicked out the about and we may be
about to us for the me being with you so
we kind of in a certain since the
relationship was what we were speaking
and you can notice how in some level
that adds a tendency to amplify what's
here amplify affinity amplify whatever
is present right so that's that kind of
bet that autopoietic flow state if you
will about that by those feelings of
Pylea as John just mentioned okay so now
what we're gonna do is we're going to do
an exercise that starts to bring in both
the present moment and sharing the
context
some of the context of your life right
so like just what's going on in your
life what it's like being you do
anything like me like you probably have
a boatload of concerns and you're a
walking bag of concerns and
considerations and you have feelings
about those things and thoughts and
circumstances and you can say that
there's layers of those in which I know
about a lot of which I don't even know
about and so what we want to do is we're
going to do it in exercise we would
break into three people right into
groups of three and one person is going
to have just two bidis just in a certain
sense you could say find yourself with
everyone there find yourself in your
life with everyone one there and then
you'll and I'll stay out with with Peter
don't put me in the rooms okay Peter for
this one after after two minutes then
what you're gonna do is is that the net
what if one of the people who is
listening is going to say basically say
and you're gonna bring in hearing that
right I'm feeling and I'm noticing right
and then and then basically what in what
I'm hearing you say is so you're
basically just gonna say what you heard
them say or a bit of what you heard them
say in the impact on you all right so
it's like hearing that guy I feel deep
joy and confusion and empathy for you
and I think what I heard was how much
you're struggling you're experiencing
struggle in this area of your life and I
found I found myself just wanting
clarity for you
right and just then we'll give you about
maybe a minute just to articulate what
you heard and what you felt right and
then the next person goes and they say
what they heard and what they felt um
for a minute and then you're gonna
switch and then the other person and
it'll be some person that kind of finds
and shares yourself and find yourself
with those two people and the intention
is when you're sharing is is to really
be a
is like to volunteer vulnerabilities of
virtue right like it's like that there's
a virtue of vulnerability John and I
were talking about this of of that not
exposure not like I'm gonna I'm gonna
embarrass myself but more like I'm gonna
I'm gonna courageously move towards the
unknown and what one of the things I've
noticed is that to the degree that to
the degree that what I'm saying is
honest is authentic is to the degree
that by definition I have no idea what's
going to happen after I say it right so
what we want to do is just speak speak
about ourselves with each other as much
as much on the edge of that as you as
you feel inclined to push for your own
comfort level okay so it beats just
simply like I'll just to get a little
bit example it's like okay so I'll just
take a deep breath I'll pretend like you
want you to pretend like I'll actually
like take a deep breath well first thing
I just notice is like a dropping and and
a sense of stillness and there's also a
sense of surprise at that stillness I
think because in my life right now
there's a circle of things outside the
stillness that are surprising that I
would be still with all those things
myself like laughing at my own
experience and then I just noticed I
caught sight of John and I'm just feel
super happy like I was feeling of warmth
in my heart just glad to be doing this
together noticing and smile and I'm a
bit overwhelmed by a few things and both
the positive and the negative sense of
the word and I feel a sense of grace
that with this sense of stillness
because this is really important for me
right now to show up for this
so that would be so that's an example of
me kind of finding myself with you guys
so you can notice I brought in some of
my own life too bye
graffitied my own life and what was
happening moment by moment it sound good
any questions all right
Obert has a question are all three
individuals going to take an opportunity
to do the primary share yes so it'll be
two minutes of sharing two minutes of
response for each person who - who had
just shared was there done then we'll
switch for another the next person will
rotate and they'll have two minutes one
minute response one minute response next
person two minutes okay and what about a
timer I mean we just do that internally
so Peter Peter do you have that function
where you can just like like I can keep
time and then we could just send a note
of yes which okay yeah well I'll do that
yeah we'll do that like note Peter will
send a little text at two minutes okay
when to start now okay two minutes is up
and you'll see a little like text
message go across the screen letting you
know okay
alright let's let's send them through
the vortex into their groups suite so
let's just take a couple of shares I
just love to hear what that experience
was like what was it it was awkward what
was like awkward about if it was
blissful what the what the qualities
were like I would like to share let's
see and um Emanuela but now that I've
broken out into a couple of rooms like
oh this is just just what I needed and
it's it's delightful
being present with me it's very
nourishing and such a minimal content
but like maximum presence is what I'm
feeling and I'm excited to keep
practicing this you all here and really
carry this out with me into the world
and you can see what kind of challenges
that come up with with art present like
how present and I continue to be when
it's not being nice thank you thank you
welcome anyone else like to share
Ari hello guy sing stock yeah yeah so I
think that as I broke out I really like
the first thing that came up for me was
I I didn't want to be around strangers
in general and I was like I was very I
was like soothed by guy and my Peter and
John who have all interacted with and
who I loved and I didn't really want to
be around strangers and I felt
underprepared those are the things that
came up I really like to be held and I
wasn't like safe with strangers and it
was a really profound experience to like
have the opposite be true of like maybe
strangers can actually be okay
could be more calming for me than people
I know you know especially with the
state of my brothers so yeah that's
really nice I met some nice people we
had a good time yeah sweet welcome Brett
pleasure of doubt yeah as we've gone
through now to to exercise I'm really
struck by the commonality of purpose in
the people I've been dialoguing with
that that those we know or don't know or
all seem to be here in a shared sense of
purpose and so even though even though
you don't know them there's there's
camaraderie that sort of forms very
quickly even in that that short time
span and you you there's that feeling
there could be more and more ongoing
dialogue and and yeah you know getting
into that personal sense of a person
where normally you don't start off
letting people in at all like that
and there's something very interesting
about this dynamic so something like a
stranger is there to say I heard this
actually at all three at some level a
stranger can evoke this sense of just
like oh oh right no wonder I mean I mean
people it's their people after all right
we could say this like people are their
people but like there are also people
right so there's a quality of like a
maybe a sense of a opposition right
right there but what's interesting I've
always and I know exactly what you're
talking about there's this quality of
like and this is where maybe the the
virtue of vulnerability starts to show
up is that it's actually the the the
affinity that you could start to feel
and the unity right in the the self
disclosure that is you know can be even
profoundly comforting as if you would
think that you would need to know that
person for a long time but there's
something right there tool is almost
like just to the left that can't seem so
far away in that kind of opponent like
instinct so that's that sense of courage
and virtue to just jump over that line
to kind of proactively take that risk
which these exercise kind of invite you
to do you could notice it's like it's
almost like a flow state that can catch
right away and then your your being can
recognize something else right something
else is possible ready in that
experience so I really appreciate all
three that I heard today so I'd turn it
over to John anything you wanted
anything you want to say about it any of
this and then we can we can move over to
to the next next exercise yeah oh no I
mean I just it was really it's always
these these circling exercises are
really wonderful appreciate them Brett
was in my group and he was another
aspect he questioned he thought up sort
of a scientific aspect yes of course
these this is an experiment and it's one
of human interaction therefore it
necessarily is a constructed environment
and of course there is a selection bias
we people are self selected to be here
so that's a relevant thing to take note
of sort of time typically breath and I
just wanted to respond to that what I
would want to say is that guy and Chris
and Peter and Jordan and I like we even
parachuting you in about sort of five
stages into this whole pedagogical
program we see people not just dropping
in but you know they've had some
practice with mindfulness and some other
things and so that it's a little bit
less that we were just getting people
who are sort of coming here with great
expectations in the Dickens sense of the
word so that's the case and then there's
also aspects of this
that would be designed to get people
come in from maybe a confrontational or
adversarial situation bad faith and move
them and share them into a more a good
faith thing to do but we were presuming
and it seems to be at least a
methodological efair presumption that
most people are here as you said with a
comma with a kind of common purpose but
there I want you to know I want you to
understand that I'm sort of from a
theoretical perspective that your what
your point isn't being ignored your
point isn't being ignored I hope that
answered the deeper the other part of
your question breath that you have so
what I would like to say now is these
practices if you allow me some more
ancient Greek so one of the things I'm
giving you is ancient Greek so you can
impress people at parties once parties
become a thing again and a lot of these
what we've done here and a lot of you
are expressing now you can give content
to this word find the up now you know
what it means
you've enacted it it's not just
something you've spoken or referred to
you've enacted by Leah now what we need
to do if we want to go forward is we've
got to integrate for Leah with Sophia
the cultivation of wisdom and that's
what we want to move to now but why am i
bringing this up
because once we go into the next
practice you need to remember the phobia
you need to recall it maybe even for a
moment do a couple of the warm-up
exercises with each other okay it's very
important that you get back into a state
of find Leah if you're going to be
cultivating find Leah Sophia so what are
we going to do and then walk you through
this next practice the practice of
dialectic again dialectic is in Thea
logos it's something we're trying to set
up a guy has a metaphor we're setting up
the logs in the right way so we can
demise the chance that the spark will
catch and the fire is as Heraclitus said
that's the logos that's the other goes
so what we're going to do is going to
divide you up into groups of four it
said I recommend you do something do a
bit maybe of the sharing so that
everybody gets into you define via then
what I'm going to ask you guys to do is
collectively choose a virtue a virtue
so it's I'll talk a little bit later I
don't want to let them burn you with
theory there's a reason why all the
Platonic dialogues are about virtue
there's a deep reason for that so gonna
pick a virtue that you can all agree on
maybe it's honesty maybe its
authenticity
maybe it's trust
maybe it's courage maybe it's the virtue
that guy is talking about vulnerability
you're gonna pick a virtue and a picot
collectively then you're gonna set the
intention you're gonna set the intention
of what we're doing here we're trying to
break out of zero sum game mindset that
our culture has deeply ingrained in us
that the point of interaction is I win
you lose the point of the interaction is
I'm right and therefore you're wrong
what we want to do is think about
instead of being right we're trying to
get into the right relationship we're
trying to get into right relationship
with each other and right relationship
with the virtue virtues aren't things
that you just think about you have to be
in the right relationship to them you
have to properly aspire to them you have
to have funnily up for them so think
about this practice as I said dialectic
is more about that we can get to a place
collectively we can afford insights
collectively that we can't get to
individually so when you're speaking
try to remember that try to remember
right relationship try to remember it
and the right relationship is also to
yourself don't just hear yourself listen
to yourself see try to listen to how
your speaking is actual is actualizing
your thinking making it present so you
said in the intention going to do this
from a place of for Lia Sophia you're
gonna try and get into right
relationship with each other and with
the virtue rather than being right about
a particular position and then you're
gonna choose you're gonna you're gonna
give yourself letters a B C and B
there's a 40 a goes first B second and
so forth person a is gonna make a
proposal don't make a statement don't
utter a proposition make a proposal for
the first person perspective I propose
that honesty is and say what you propose
and mean it both senses like that you
have some clear sense of what you're
saying and that you're willing to stand
behind it don't don't don't don't just
you know don't be fatuous just say like
mean it show up in it now that person a
will will be right speaking to everybody
but in particular to person B and what
person B you're doing actually a lot of
the hard work we tend to focus too much
on what's being said and not enough on
how things are being listened to in our
culture and so the person B is you're
going to do this three-step process
you're gonna first of all amplify what
person a is saying you're gonna
periodically and the speaker pause speak
slowly put pauses in your speech so that
the other person has an opportunity to
respond
so when you amplify you offer no
criticism no criticism one more time no
criticism you are listening and what
you're doing at this stage is you're
trying to draw the person out that's
what education means adduce to draw out
you're gonna ask them well how does it
feel in your mind to say what you said
how does it feel in your body I noticed
that you were you clenched her hand can
you go back and close your hand again
what does it feel like when you do that
I noticed you use this image of light go
into that image what does it feel like
you're gonna try to draw the person out
because what you're trying to do is
you're trying to get them to pay
attention not only to what they're
saying about the virtue honesty but also
how they're exemplifying it how they're
enacting it how it's here right now in
what they're doing
you're trying to get them to say more
and be more about the virtue sometimes
just say to them well can you say more
can you say more you do that for let's
say five minutes there's a proposal and
a keeps proposing and B keeps amplifying
until a point where that five minutes is
up and a sort of like okay that's enough
for now because this is very demanding
go do it then B moves from amplifying to
appreciated three senses of the word
understood when we say we appreciating
music music appreciation
so what B does is first has to say back
to a this is what I heard you saying
this is how I this is what I heard in
your proposal
I heard you proposing this right and
you're trying to summarize everything
that a has said an exemplified this is
how what I've heard and you have to do B
has to do that until they goes yes
you've heard me that's what I said if
you can't get to that stage stop cuz
you can't go farther until that there is
that acknowledgment second part of
appreciation B says what they found
valuable like wow I have you thought
about that before I really appreciate
that that that take on honesty it may it
made me think of something I hadn't
thought about her but give me a bit of
an insight or a new angle on honesty I
really value that thank you
I can see how that could be helpful to
me as I try to be a more honest person
so amplification appreciation and then
what B does is the now moves to
anticipation this is B now anticipating
how on what a has said B is going to try
and come up with their own proposal and
so what B does is it for here's where
you can now in some sense challenge what
he says he can say what was missing an
AIDS proposal
you know these proposal was great but
there was an aspect of honesty that I
don't think was there this is part of I
think that there's more to honesty this
is what the more or what was mistaken
for house but there's an assumption here
that I kind of like the challenge about
honesty and then also what was
mysterious perhaps Wow there was
something strange or I get this weird
sense of there being something more to
honesty that I couldn't quite grasp so
what was missing what was mistaken what
was mysterious
everything from the first-person
perspective this is what I feel was
missing this is what I feel or think is
mistaken this is what I found mysterious
then B turns to C and makes a proposal I
propose that honesty is blood and then
she does the amplification the
appreciation and the anticipation and
then see eventually makes a proposal to
D who does the amplification the
appreciation and the anticipation and
then passes it back to a so a will
ultimately amplify and appreciate and
respond to deep and you go through the
cycle so try to be respectful of the
time you're sharing the time try to
remember to not like it's very hard okay
when you eat but you are in the service
of the proposer until it comes to the
anticipation stage right you're
amplifying and appreciating and only
then do you move into anticipation and
only after that do you then make your
proposal to the next person any
questions about this you also have the
you also have the document any questions
about this run this before and it is it
does work I strongly recommend like I
said that you perhaps when you first get
together you just do the noticing each
other for each for the four of you get
back into that fight here get back into
that friendlier
okay so like I said this is all so be
patient with yourselves this is going to
feel clumsy and clunky to some degree
that's a question thing yes Brett so is
there a problem with taking notes so he
could have better recall no take notes
do what you need to do in order to be as
responsible as you can to the proposer
so this will be challenging because one
of the things that induces the flow
state is that people have to get into
what's called the zone of proximal
development they have to get into
something that challenges their skill
their skills beyond which beyond normal
so play with this play with it it's
designed to challenge you any other
question
am I missing anything Peter is it does
anybody have a hand up that I'm missing
okay so Peter I should also stay out of
the room this time okay is everybody
clear what you're doing you have the
document is everybody okay so yeah yes
what they just just so you know John and
myself may pop into the room yay and pop
out because we won't be jumping around
cuz part of what we're doing is like
really kind of checking it out and
seeing what runs and what we're
experiencing so you see yes just ignore
us yeah just ignore us and don't be
intimidated please be very much like my
childhood you know okay everyone have
fun with it please Sirius play and how
long do they have as long as you want it
would be good if we had at least 15
minutes where we return to the giant
room gotcha okay cool
they're even rooms have been opened very
cool very cool how did it go guy that's
great
I really I it was great I thought it was
great okay so it would be good if we
three didn't talk too much right now
this way I don't want to lose the fire
of what's happened okay can everybody
hear me because we're still not during
the practice so now we're gonna make the
final move and now it's pretty much
right we're gonna have to do a
parliamentary style so we don't get
feedback and weird crap like that but
now I want us all very freeform
to address this question based on what's
been happening in your own room what is
virtue just let's start getting some
answers what is virtue Daniel
Lockhart remember to unmute yourself
please virtue is something you can talk
about endlessly very good so virtue is
something you can talk about endlessly
let's keep going more feedback let's
build on this let's rip on each other
this is collected jazz what is Richard
David done virtue is a process it's like
an inquiry so what did what so christian
guys when you give an answer you know
feel free to refer to what happened in
your own room so move between the
general and the particular as freely as
you feel now yeah let's say virtue is a
process that too active at its on I
notice it it's like a commitment to do
good regardless of what happens there's
a sort of faith there there's a sort of
faith there interesting more feedback
keep going I say it's the heart of being
alive part of being alive can you that's
really perfect that's really provoked
I'm gonna go all on Blaikie in on
everyone and just say its energy its
energy oh these are great can some of
you like I say try these abstract ideas
to what concretely happened in your own
breakout rooms to doing this but also
yeah we were we were just riffing off
each other it was so good like somebody
started with something I was like you
know that's great and I have you know
have another take on it and person three
was like oh here's where the boundary
was between this and that I'm gonna
explore that boundary great it's so cool
what happened but let's keep on this
question you had your hand up you wanted
to say what virtualize yeah I would say
it's a it's a it's a it's a slowdown
good-faith iterative process of truth
seeking refinement whoa that's very cool
very cool
good morning somewhere keep going keep
tripping right look it's the pursuit of
the good without falling off the edge so
can you say a little bit more about that
what you mean by their falling off the
edge about you know if you approach the
extreme you can you can we're gonna we
did curiosity which can lead to full
hardiness and recklessness if if pursued
too much so so there you want a
temperate but if you temperate too
little you don't have any movement at
all so it's it's about moving forward
well well
so pursuing the good while avoiding the
exploiting the extreme what can I rip
off of that oh yeah I was in the same
room with that I was in the same room
with Brett and because we were
discussing curiosity we eventually
arrived at the idea that curiosity is
the driver of reciprocal opening with
reality but because it's the driver of
reciprocal opening you can become to
open and fall off the edge of aw into
terror
and thus begin a cycle of reciprocal
closing merrily and that's to be avoided
that's good what happened there between
breath an ominous was really really good
for that that we also in my break room
talked about um reciprocity we ended up
going with honesty you know but
reciprocity and then it kind of went to
the threat of connection just connecting
with anything whether your own is to
make sure you actually connect
reciprocate that you know so maybe
virtue is also just being able to form
deeper connections with people kind of
like Kate said in a way which I would
think is also very a part of life the
connections you make with other people
I'd like to I'd like to add to that yes
yeah so what I'm hearing there is that
it's an it's an enrichment of the bond
formed between two or more people that
that that blossoms choice that fort for
everyone so with the enrichment of the
bond it I feel like so for me when we
were discussing it it felt like
uncovering something that is inherent
like something that we're discovering
that's already there uncovering yeah
that that sense of that sense of virtue
is that which is covering over what's
guiding me that when it's revealed I've
realized it was obvious the whole time
yeah the idea yeah the idea of
uncovering was coming up for me it was
the the idea that it's some aspect of
our highest essence kind of like one
facet of our Dimond that we can only
never quite get to but always keep
taking good-faith stabs that together do
it for you my word she feels subjective
based on my level of
awareness hmm so Ben has his hand up for
quite a while then please um I get a
feeling of dancing and balance over the
golden mean we're just trying we're just
trying to get that that sweet spot yeah
and not to go too far like to go far
enough
just like in flow and then when we hit
it that feels like
pochi right right right so I yeah I'm
just gonna riff on on dance because what
came up in our conversation was this
idea of this and and we were we were
discussing authenticity but that there
was this harmonious dance where all of
these layers of motivation had to be
kind of seen through there had to be
this absence of self-deception and that
ultimately for me it felt like it was
this this this positive quality that
arises out of out of integration you
know out of just the sort of seamless
integration when all yeah all of these
layers have just kind of been
synthesized and and are now and are now
just in balance so if I can comment here
notice how many of you are doing the
integration of five Ilia with Sofia and
you're going into like this right
relationship this evolving relationship
this living relationship it's really
really really impressive I I'm very
impressed
really so I know we could do this part
for a long time but we only have five
minutes left and I'd like to move now to
stepping out of the dialectic we're
going to be doing this again so we're
gonna have an opportunity and so now
some meta discussion you some of you
have already thrown it in so maybe a
couple of reflections on the whole thing
to have
and tonight and comments concerns
connections reflections Brett this was
great just just a little problem we ran
into in the last session is we ran out
of time we only got to see and so having
those timers is probably is really
helpful to keep to keep things on track
yep Megan hey I'm just pointing out a
weak typo you've got in your description
the person a description
step one is copy pasted from above so
the letters are exchanged we did figure
out what is supposed to be person C step
one anyway thank you for that we'll make
sure that that's correct next time then
I feel like a child making a discovery
and I have to practice more more more
good good because that's you know wisdom
begins in wonder and so that's a good
place to be that's a good place to be
Socrates would be happy with what you
just said I have a quick question a
quick reflection on choosing the virtue
which we did collectively which I think
was useful but we didn't have we kind of
I think could choose from any virtue at
all and I wonder if that was accurate
that that's that's kind of and then the
collective coming to the collective
choosing is that also part of part of it
so that's why so you have some resonance
between or between each other
so that collective choice can be made
fairly spontaneously and intuitively but
not just superficially exactly exactly
Claudia so I'd like to there's a lot uh
there's a lot going on here about I even
our group came to this metaphor of the
wave and then being on the ocean riding
away I feel
feeling a moment comes and knowing if
that's your moment to actually ride on
this thing and find your limits in there
oh that waves are too big for me I had
this wave is perfectly just too small I
can feel it now is this the right moment
for me to talk what should I bet it
earlier it's really really beautiful oh
that's that's that's exactly you know I
grew up where people used to talk about
catching a wave and that's what I was
trying to convey with catch the logos
and so Cody that's exactly that's
exactly the sort of sensibility that I'm
trying to get people into so thank you
for that reflection so we were pretty
much done our time and I'd like to turn
it back over to guide to sort of close
things up for us
sweet I was that was really that was
really fun thank you everybody for
playing with us
do you think so the plan is right now is
we're gonna meet every other I think
it's every other Tuesday yep at this
time ongoingly and so will will John and
I will we'll meet and we'll kind of talk
about it and make adjustments and then
we'll come back in and we'll probably do
another participatory like that as you
can see this the experience of
participation like participatory knowing
is is that we want to dive into so any
feedback any insights that you get any
like anything's around like we
misspelled the word all those things
very very welcome and I'm a really glad
that you are a part of this a couple
things is that that are available as
many of you know I my companies the
circling Institute and then we've we've
just recently moved all of our all of
our stuff online and so we have like an
open thing on Thursday evening that you
can you can come to and we also have a
like I think a weekend course a circling
course in a couple of weeks and like and
also a whole kind of training so I will
we I can I can just send them a link
over email or some
right Peter yeah you can send it to me I
can also put my mailing list to so
everyone has access to it okay yeah I'll
give him the just the links and all that
kind of stuff the other thing is is is
you know you know you can go to on
John's channel he's he has a lot of
examples of him and dialogue in dialo
goes you you can go on my channels I
mean there's just lots of there's lots
of lots of moments and the thing I would
encourage you to do is it's just like
kind of what was said here there is a
place where it's like something starts
to catch right
something starts to catch where you
recognize that you recognize that oh
we're all or I'm like somehow responding
to this thing that I wasn't even
tracking with that was responding to but
he was granting I was moving towards
something this kind of disclosure so I
just want to I want to encourage like if
you if you watch any of the videos see
if you can just notice like moments
where it just catches like notice that
like moments were where somebody's
talking about something or the
conversation just ignites right with the
logo cat though the logos catches and
then just allow this allow this
conversation to just well with you and
walk with you and just notice your life
like let your life inform the insights
that are happening and then come back
next week and we'll play some more it's
just next week good guy throws bi-weekly
I'm sorry like every other Everton's
yeah cool cool thank you all for your
courage and your the way you showed up
and this I think this is an important
project and so I'm deeply appreciative
of everybody's participation and
involvement in feedback I want to thank
especially Peter for hosting this and
making this possible so thank you very
much yeah thank you Peter thank you John
thank you guys thank you everyone for
for coming today so we'll be here the
week after this video not the breakout
room so that wasn't recorded but to kind
of the main thing will be put a post on
YouTube hopefully uh this evening so you
can wash it again practice on your own
and then come to the store for the
wisdom gym we have a just announced a
couple events that are coming up we have
a raw sexuality dark guys and maybe gray
series that's at 8:30 today so about 30
minutes you go on the website and then
Joe lead them in the social design Club
talking about social design systems that
set tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. Eastern Time
that's gonna be a lot of fun and the
stoechas based off a gift economy I'm
viewing it as a gift thrust you freely
use this time of need your aspire to buy
the gift to the store or any of our
wonderful facilitators you can call this
website right here and then guy and John
I would love to have you guys and then
you're cool illustration on that page
too so people you can have your
information on it as well alright thank
you so much everyone
Oh everyone thank you